<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/4.5" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/4.5 http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xsd/4.5/docbook.xsd">

	<title>Atomic transformations (data cleaning as a service)</title>

	<chapterinfo>
		<abstract>
			<para>
				In this chapter we will learn how to use the DataCleaner
				monitor as a web service for invoking DataCleaner jobs as on-demand
				/ on-the-fly data cleansing operations.
				Like in the case of
				repository navigation, these web services are located with URLs
				starting with the form:
			</para>
			<para>/DataCleaner-monitor/repository/DC/...
			</para>
			<para>Where 'DC' is the tenant identifier and 'DataCleaner-monitor'
				is the web application archive name.
			</para>
		</abstract>
	</chapterinfo>

	<section>
		<title>What are atomic transformation services?</title>

		<para>DataCleaner jobs normally operate on batches of records, for
			example all records in a CSV file. However, any DataCleaner job can
			also be used to process single records on the fly. This feature is
			called "atomic transformations". Such transformations could be used
			as a part of a data processing pipeline in a SOA architecture or in a
			web application with flexible data processing needs.</para>

		<para>Creating an atomic transformation is easy. Any DataCleaner job
			can be used for performing atomic transformations. Simply create a
			job that does some kind of transformation (anything from a simple
			'String length' operation to a complete chain of 'Address cleansing'
			and regex parsing), and place the job in the DataCleaner monitor
			repository. A specialized web service endpoint will be automatically
			exposed to use the job as an atomic transformation. The endpoint URL
			will be:
		</para>

		<programlisting>
			/DataCleaner-monitor/repository/DC/jobs/[jobname].invoke
		</programlisting>

	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Invoking atomic transformations</title>

		<para>The contract of the atomic transformation invocation service is
			dynamic, based on the contract defined by source data and transformed
			data in the job.
		</para>
		<para>The web service is based on JSON data. You need to provide the
			JSON data corresponding to the source record format of the job.
		</para>

		<para>For instance, let's say a job defines the following JavaScript
			transformation with two source columns (POSTALCODE and COUNTRY):
		</para>

		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="webservice_atomic_transformation_example.jpg"
					scalefit="1" format="JPG" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>

		<para>The web service will therefore expect that each JSON record
			contains two values. The service accepts one or multiple records in
			it's payload. Use a HTTP POST with a body like this (3 records and 2
			columns):
		</para>

		<programlisting>
			{"rows":[
			&#160;&#160;{"values":["2200","DK"]},
			&#160;&#160;{"values":["2200",""]},
			&#160;&#160;{"values":["DK2200","DK"]}
			]}
		</programlisting>

		<para>And the resulting response body will look like this:</para>

		<programlisting>
			{
			&#160;&#160;"rows":[
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;{"values":["DK2200"]},
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;{"values":["2200"]},
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;{"values":["DK2200"]}
			&#160;&#160;],
			&#160;&#160;"columns":[
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;"Country postalcode"
			&#160;&#160;]
			}
		</programlisting>

		<para>Note that the 'Content-Type' header of the request is assumed to
			be 'application/json'.
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
