<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/4.5"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/4.5 http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xsd/4.5/docbook.xsd">

	<title>Extension packaging</title>

	<chapterinfo>
		<abstract>
			<para>
				DataCleaner extensions are packages of added functionality,
				written in Java. To correctly package an extension, this chapter will
				walk through the details.
			</para>
		</abstract>
	</chapterinfo>

	<section>
		<title>Annotated component</title>
		<para>The main principle behind extension discovery in DataCleaner is
			annotated classes. These are the annotations that will work to
			activate components within your extension:
		</para>

		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				@AnalyzerBean
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				@TransformerBean
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				@FilterBean
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				@RendererBean
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<para>Please refer to the javadoc documentation of these
			annotations/classes for details on usage.
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Single JAR file</title>
		<para>The extension must consist of a single JAR file. If you have
			dependencies other than the libraries provided by the DataCleaner
			distribution, you need to package these inside your own JAR file. If
			you're using Maven for your build, the Maven Assembly Plugin can
			provide this functionality easily using this snippet in your POM:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
			&lt;build&gt;
			&#160;&lt;plugins&gt;
			&#160;&#160;&lt;plugin&gt;
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&lt;groupId&gt;org.apache.maven.plugins&lt;/groupId&gt;
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&lt;artifactId&gt;maven-assembly-plugin&lt;/artifactId&gt;
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&lt;version&gt;2.2.1&lt;/version&gt;
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&lt;configuration&gt;
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&lt;descriptorRefs&gt;
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&lt;descriptorRef&gt;jar-with-dependencies&lt;/descriptorRef&gt;
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&lt;/descriptorRefs&gt;
			&#160;&#160;&#160;&lt;/configuration&gt;
			&#160;&#160;&lt;/plugin&gt;
			&#160;&lt;/plugins&gt;
			&lt;/build&gt; </programlisting>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Component icons</title>
		<para>If you wish to add a custom icon for your components (eg. a
			transformer or analyzer), you need to place the icon as a PNG image
			with the same name as the fully classified class name of the
			component.
		</para>
		<para>An example: If your component class name is
			"com.company.ext.MyAnalyzer", then the icon for this component should
			be located at "/com/company/ext/MyAnalyzer.png" in the extension JAR
			file.
		</para>
		<para>Similarly, if you bundle your own ComponentCategory
			implementations (which define the menu groups in DataCleaner), you
			can define icons for these by adding a PNG file with a fully
			classified filename corresponding to the ComponentCategory class
			name.
		</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
