<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/4.5" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/4.5 http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xsd/4.5/docbook.xsd">

	<title>Analyzers</title>

	<para>This chapter deals with one of the most important concepts in
		DataCleaner: Analyzers. Analyzers are the endpoints of any analysis
		job, meaning that a job requires at least on analyzer.</para>
	<para>An analyzer consumes a (set of) column(s) and generates an
		analysis result based on the values in the consumed columns.</para>
	<para>Here is an example of a configuration panel pertaining to an
		analyzer:</para>
	<mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="analysis_job_04_analyzer.jpg" format="JPG" scalefit="1" />
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	<para>In the panel there will always be one or more selections of
		columns. The configuration panel may also contain additional
		properties for configuration.</para>

	<section id="boolean_analyzer">
		<title>Boolean analyzer</title>
		<para>Boolean analyzer is an analyzer targeted at boolean values. For
			a single boolean column it is quite simple: It will show the
			distribution of true/false (and optionally null) values in a column.
			For several columns it will also show the value combinations and the
			frequencies of the combinations. The combination matrix makes the
			Boolean analyzer a handy analyzer for use with combinations of
			matching transformers and other transformers that yield boolean
			values.</para>
		<para>Boolean analyzer has no configuration parameters, except for the
			input columns.</para>
	</section>

	<section id="character_set_distribution">
		<title>Character set distribution</title>
		<para>The Character set distribution analyzer inspects and maps text
			characters according to character set affinity, such as Latin,
			Hebrew, Cyrillic, Chinese and more.</para>
		<para>Such analysis is convenient for getting insight into the
			international aspects of your data. Are you able to read and
			understand all your data? Will it work in your non-internationalized
			systems?</para>
	</section>

	<section id="date_dap_analyzer">
		<title>Date gap analyzer</title>
		<para>TODO</para>
	</section>

	<section id="date_time_analyzer">
		<title>Date/time analyzer</title>
		<para>TODO</para>
	</section>

	<section id="matching_analyzer">
		<title>Matching analyzer</title>
		<para>TODO</para>
	</section>

	<section id="number_analyzer">
		<title>Number analyzer</title>
		<para>TODO</para>
	</section>

	<section id="pattern_finder">
		<title>Pattern finder</title>
		<para>The pattern finder is one of the more advanced, but also very
			popular analyzers of DataCleaner.</para>
		<para>Here is a screenshot of the configuration panel of the Pattern
			finder:</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="analyzer_reference_pattern_finder.jpg"
					format="JPG" scalefit="1" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<para>From the screenshot we can see that the Pattern finder has these
			configuration properties:</para>
		<table>
			<title>Pattern finder properties</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Property</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Group column</entry>
						<entry>Allows you to define a pattern group column. With a pattern
							group column you can separate the identified patterns into
							separate buckets/groups. Imagine for example that you want to
							check if the phone numbers of your customers are consistent. If
							you have an international customer based, you should then group
							by a country column to make sure that phone patterns identified
							are not matched with phone patterns from different countries.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Discriminate text case</entry>
						<entry>Defines whether or not to discriminate (ie. consider as
							different pattern parts) based on text case. If true
							"DataCleaner" and "datacleaner" will be considered instances of
							different patterns, if false they will be matched within same
							pattern.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Discriminate negative numbers</entry>
						<entry>When parsing numbers, this property defines if negative
							numbers should be discriminated from positive numbers.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Discriminate decimals</entry>
						<entry>When parsing numbers, this property defines if decimal
							numbers should be discriminated from integers.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Enable mixed tokens</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>Defines whether or not to categorize tokens that contain
								both letters and digits as "mixed", or alternatively as two
								separate tokens. Mixed tokens are represented using questionmark
								('?')
								symbols.</para>
							<para>This is one of the more important configuration properties.
								For example if mixed tokens are enabled (default), all these
								values will
								be matched against the same pattern: foo123, 123foo,
								foobar123, foo123bar. If mixed tokens are NOT enabled only
								foo123 and foobar123 will be matched (because 123foo and
								foo123bar represent different combinations of letter and digit
								tokens).</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Ignore repeated spaces</entry>
						<entry>Defines whether or not to discriminate based on amount of
							whitespaces.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Upper case patterns expand in size</entry>
						<entry>Defines whether or not upper case tokens automatically
							"expand" in size. Expandability refers to whether or not the
							found patterns will include matches if a candidate has the same
							type of token, but with a different size. The default
							configuration for upper case characters is false (ie. ABC is
							not
							matched with ABCD).</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Lower case patterns expand in size</entry>
						<entry>
							<para>Defines whether or not lower case tokens automatically
								"expand" in size. As with upper case expandability, this
								property
								refers to whether or not the found patterns will include
								matches
								if a candidate has the same type of token, but with a
								different
								size. The default configuration for lower case
								characters is
								true
								(ie. 'abc' is not matched with 'abc').</para>
							<para>The defaults in the two "expandability" configuration
								properties mean that eg. name pattern recognition is meaningful:
								'James' and 'John' both pertain to the same pattern ('Aaaaa'),
								while 'McDonald' pertain to a different pattern ('AaAaaaaa').
							</para>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Predefined token name</entry>
						<entry>Predefined tokens make it possible to define a token to
							look for and classify using either just a fixed list of values or
							regular expressions. Typically this is used if the values contain
							some additional parts which you want to manually define a
							matching category for. The 'Predefined token name' property
							defines the name of such a category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Predefined token regexes</entry>
						<entry>Defines a number of string values and/or regular
							expressions which are used to match values against the
							(pre)defined token category.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Decimal separator</entry>
						<entry>The decimal separator character, used when parsing numbers
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Thousand separator</entry>
						<entry>The thousand separator character, used when parsing numbers
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Minus sign</entry>
						<entry>The minus sign character, used when parsing numbers</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</section>

	<section id="string_analyzer">
		<title>String analyzer</title>
		<para>TODO</para>
	</section>

	<section id="value_distribution">
		<title>Value distribution</title>
		<para>TODO</para>
		<para>Here are the configuration properties for the value distribution
			analyzer:</para>
		<table>
			<title>Value distribution properties</title>
			<tgroup cols="2">
				<thead>
					<row>
						<entry>Property</entry>
						<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Group column</entry>
						<entry>Allows you to define a column for grouping the result. With
							a
							group column you can separate the identified value distributions
							into
							separate buckets/groups. Imagine for example that you want to
							check if the postal codes and city names correspond or if you
							just want to segment your value distribution on eg. country or
							gender or ...
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Record unique values</entry>
						<entry>By default all unique values will be included in the result
							of the value distribution. This can potentially cause memory
							issues if your analyzed columns contains a LOT of unique values
							(eg. if it's a unique key). If the actual unique values are not
							of interest, then uncheck this checkbox to only count (but not
							save for inspection) the unique values.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Top n most frequent vales</entry>
						<entry>An optional number used if the analysis should only display
							eg. the "top 5 most frequent values". The result of the analysis
							will only contain top/bottom n most frequent values, if this
							property is supplied.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Bottom n most frequent values</entry>
						<entry>An optional number used if the analysis should only display
							eg. the "bottom 5 most frequent values". The result of the
							analysis
							will only contain top/bottom n most frequent values, if
							this
							property is supplied.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</section>

	<section id="weekday_distribution">
		<title>Weekday distribution</title>
		<para>TODO</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
