<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
	<title>DataCleaner reference documentation</title>
	<titleabbrev>DataCleaner</titleabbrev>
	<bookinfo>
		<author>
			<personname>
				<firstname>Kasper</firstname>
				<surname>S&#248;rensen</surname>
			</personname>
		</author>
		<edition>1.5-SNAPSHOT</edition>
	</bookinfo>
	<preface id="preface1">
		<title>Preface</title>
		<para>
			Data quality is an issue too often ignored. With almost any type of application,
			datastore or document comes a set of potential data quality pitfalls. DataCleaner
			was founded upon the idea of promoting data quality awareness and bringing it to the
			general public. This required a drastic change from the strategy that commercial data
			quality products are practicing. If we want the general public to be aware of the
			data quality domain, then we have to provide them with the tools to experience it themselves.
		</para>
		<para>
			Although we recognize that dedicated data quality analysis is, and probably
			always will be, a professional niche with a limited audience, we believe that for the most part,
			data quality tools should be free and developed in coorporation and participation between
			those professionals. Since data quality in many ways represents a "common good" and a an
			issue of general interest, we believe in this model of shared ownership and responsibility. This
			is why DataCleaner was founded as an Open Source project and we hope that the implifications of
			the Open Source philosophy will influence the products future in a positive way.
		</para>
	</preface>
	<chapter>
		<title>Introduction to the concepts and features of DataCleaner</title>
		<section>
			<title>What is Data Quality?</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>What is Open Source software?</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Data Profiling</title>
			<para>
				The profiler is used to calculate and analyse various important measures based on the values of data.
				In this sense the results of a profiling will always have to be read and contemplated upon by a
				physical person, for example a Database Administrator, BI engineer or similar. The results are
				supposed to help this person determine where to look for data quality problem in the data source -
				to get an impression of the state of the data.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Data Validation</title>
			<para>
				In contrast to the profiler and the comparator, the validator will give you a result that can be
				interpreted as "good" or "bad", since the validator validates your data. In the validator-mode you
				set up business rules that apply to your data and recieve a result that can be used to fix
				validation errors.
			</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Installation and configuration</title>
		<para>This chapter covers the installation and configuration of DataCleaner.</para>
		<section>
			<title>Software requirements</title>
			<para>
				DataCleaner requires a Java Runtime Environment (JRE) version 5.0 or higher.
				You can download the JRE at Sun Microsystems Java website:
			</para>
			<para>
				<ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads">http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads</ulink>
			</para>
			<para>
				DataCleaner runs in both desktop-application mode and command-line interface mode on
				Microsoft Windows Operating Systems, Mac OS X and Linux. For optimal performance, a minimum
				of 1024 megabytes (1 gigabyte) of free memory is recommended.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Database drivers</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Database connections</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Dictionaries</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Regular Expressions (regexes)</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>The DataCleaner desktop-applicatoin</title>
		<section>
			<title>What is the desktop-application used for?</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>The Profiler</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>The Validator</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>The Comparator</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>The DataCleaner command-line interface</title>
		<section>
			<title>What is the command-line interface used for?</title>
			<para>TODO: Running batches of DQ analysis, automation, etc.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Running a DataCleaner job</title>
			<para>TODO: calling runjob.sh/.cmd</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Output formats</title>
			<para>TODO: XML and CSV output formats</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Scheduling jobs</title>
			<para>TODO: Examples of scheduling using cron and Scheduled Tasks</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Developers guide</title>
		<section>
			<title>Java API reference documentation</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>An introduction to the architecture of DataCleaner</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Understanding the DataCleaner ecosystem</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Developing custom profiles</title>
			<para>TODO</para>
		</section>
	</chapter>
</book>