<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/4.5" xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/4.5 http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xsd/4.5/docbook.xsd">

	<title>Database drivers</title>

	<chapterinfo>
		<abstract>
			<para>
				DataCleaner ships with a set of standard database drivers,
				enabling you to connect to common databases such as PostgreSQL,
				MySQL, Microsoft SQL Server or Oracle.
			</para>
			<para>It's also not uncommon to wish to install additional drivers
				for other database brands. DataCleaner uses the JDBC standard for
				managing database drivers and connection. In this chapter we cover
				the process of installing additional database drivers.
			</para>
		</abstract>
	</chapterinfo>

	<section id="database_drivers_desktop">
		<title>Installing Database drivers in DataCleaner desktop</title>

		<para>Installing database drivers in DataCleaner desktop is done in
			the application itself while it is running.
		</para>
		<para>First, go to the Options menu:</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="database_drivers_desktop_menu.png"
					format="PNG" scalefit="1" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<para>Then select the 'Database drivers' tab. In this tab you will see
			a listing of your currently installed database drivers (that we know
			of):
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="database_drivers_desktop_listing.png"
					format="PNG" scalefit="1" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<para>If you click the 'Add database driver' button and then select
			the 'Local JAR file(s)' option, you will see this dialog:
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="database_drivers_desktop_dialog.png"
					format="PNG" scalefit="1" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
		<para>In this dialog, select driver class name and the files
			containing the database driver. If you don't know what this is please
			refer to your database vendor's documentation on JDBC database
			drivers.
		</para>

		<para>In the example above we see the IBM
			DB2 driver which involves
			installing two files since the software
			license also has to be
			included.
		</para>

	</section>

	<section id="database_drivers_server">
		<title>Installing Database drivers in DataCleaner monitor</title>
		<para>If you want to install database drivers in the DataCleaner
			monitor web application, you should first consider if you want the
			driver installed only as part of the single web application or if it
			should be globally registered within your web server/container.
		</para>

		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Installing database driver in Container</emphasis>
					: Refer to your container's documentation. Usually the process is a
					simple matter of copying the driver JAR files to a folder in the
					web container's workspace. For instance, if you're using Apache
					Tomcat, copy the driver JAR file(s) to the 'lib' folder of Tomcat.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					<emphasis>Installing database driver in the web application
					</emphasis>
					: First, locate where the DataCleaner monitor .war file is deployed
					and 'exploded' into a directory. Within this directory you will
					find the folder 'WEB-INF/lib'. Copy the database driver file(s) into
					this directory.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>

		<para>We recommend installing drivers in the container. This makes your web application easier to upgrade and manage.</para>
	</section>

</chapter>
